Ese Udom

Lagos, Nigeria

udomese@yahoo.com • +234 706 069 0440 https://github.com/esecoder • https://gitlab.com/EseCoder

Professional Summary

I am an IT expert with software development, project management, problem-solving, and ideagenerating skills. I have been in the industry since 2012, working in software development training, music streaming, Android OSes, and open-source software. I have designed, built, and maintained mobile, desktop, and web apps some of which are hosted on the cloud (AWS) and deployed as MVC, MVP, and MVVM infrastructures.

I have built projects using Java, Kotlin, PHP/Laravel, Javascript, XML, and HTML/CSS.

Recently, I have played around with the Android Open Source Project (AOSP) and built a Firewall system app and 4 other apps with the CalyxOS team. I plan to contribute more open-source software with them and other open-source teams. I have an encrypted telephone voice call app in the works as part of my contributions. My remote work with the international no-profit organizations Internews and the Calyx Institute can prove my ability to work remotely effectively.

Technical Skills

- Java Programming
- Android Applications Development and Android XML
- Native Android Development
- SDKs
- Data Structures and Algorithms
- AWS cloud deployment and management
- Codename One
- Kotlin
- AOSP
- Containerization(Docker/Kubernetes)
- CI/CD (Heroku/Bitbucket/CircleCI)
- iOS Development (Beginner level)
- Git/Gerrit
- HTML 5/CSS, XML, JSON
- SQL (Expert)
- Testing (JUnit, Espresso, Mockito)

- Architecture Design (MVVM, MVP, MVC)
- JSON
- SOLID Principles
- MySQL/PostgresSQL Databases
- NoSQL (MongoDb)
- JavaScript
- NodeJS
- PHP/Laravel and Web Backend development
- Java Backend(Spring Boot)
- API design and development
- ReactJS, AngularJS, Angular2, JQuery, Bootstrap
- Google Platform
- AutoCAD
- API (REST, GraphQL)
- C#
- C/C++

Work History

UX/Android Engineer (Consultant), 01/2021 to 03/2022

Internews, Washington DC, United States , Calyx Institute, New York, United States, Horizontal, Los Angeles, United States

- Member of a team of engineers and security experts distributed around the world to build and maintain a free custom mobile OS (CalyxOS) based on the AOSP (Android Open Source Project). Calyx is built with privacy as priority. Picture an Android OS but without all the Google services to track your every move.
- Member of the Tella team. https://github.com/Horizontal-org/Tella-Android
- Building and maintaining apps for the platform and working with a very experienced team including popular American system engineers and security researchers using Gerrit and Gitlab pipeline.
- Work extensively on AOSP
- Directly involved with the Calyx Datura Firewall system app https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/platform packages apps Firewall
- Directly involved with the Calyx Blossom Muzei source system app https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/blossom
- Directly involved with the Calyx Muzei wallpaper app https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/muzei
- Directly involved with the Calyx Feedback app, Buttercup.
 https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/platform_packages apps Buttercup
- Directly involved with the Calyx Bubbles.
 https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/platform packages apps Bubbles
- Work with system APIs
- Collaborate with a diverse distributed team
- Use Git, Gerrit, and Gitlab extensively for collaboration and code reviews
- Work on extensively on network and security system APIs
- Learned a lot about OS Engineering
- Work with people from 5 continents and different time zones

https://calyxos.org

https://calyxos.org/get

https://calyxos.org/get/install

https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS

https://calyxinstitute.org

Senior Software Engineer, 05/2018 to 01/2021

MePlaylist Classic Entertainment Ltd, Ikeja, Lagos

- Team Lead for a group of engineers that developed and deployed a mobile music streaming Android app hosted on AWS.
 - https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=app.meplaylist.com.meplay
- Maintaining and optimizing the mobile app together with a small team comprising web developers and data managers.

- Facilitating team collaboration in remotely distributed software teams in Nigeria and The US.
- Managing our large MySQL database of millions of records and hundreds of thousands of content and growing. Also writing expert level SQL algorithms to fetch content in milliseconds to users and for analytics.
- Configured and currently managing our AWS infrastructure (3 EC2 instances, S3 Buckets, and 2 RDS instances).
- Integrating many third-party APIs and SDKs including audio ads (Triton), Google Ads, social media log-ins (Facebook, Google), and payments (Flutterwave).
- Building a DDEX metadata parser (NICK 2.0), which parses complex XML data to JSON and PHP Object for analysis and storage.
- Building, configuring, and maintaining our Apache2 server back-end.
- Building and maintaining the back-end application and documenting its APIs which powers the Android, iOS, and Web applications.
- Integrated third-party APIs ranging from ads (Triton) to payments (Flutterwave).
- Using Android ExoPlayer media player library to implement music and ads streaming.
- Integrating the Triton Ads SOAP APIs for audio ads by parsing XML data into the streaming pipeline between playback intervals
- Integrating Flutterwave, GTBank, and Opay payment APIs by parsing JSON data and building with SDK
- Integrating Google Ads banner and interstitial ads with the API.
- Integrating Firebase push notifications.
- Building and documenting PHP backend server with RESTful APIs to serve Android and iOS mobile apps as well as web app.
- Configuring and managing the Apache server that hosts and serves our web server application for all app clients.
- Setting up, configuring, and maintaining the AWS EC2 instance for and installing Apache and PHP for the webserver application.
- Integrating Flutterwave payment in PHP for the backend application. Also building cron jobs for payment renewals, checks, and reminders.
- Integrating Firebase in PHP using an SDK for push notifications from the backend into the mobile apps. Notifications for new content, actions, etc.
- Integrating AWS SDK for some content management.
- Building an audio transcoder to transcode 320kbps mp3 audio to 192 kbps and also WAV files to MP3 files.
- Building an image size converter to reduce image sizes of music cover pictures.
- Configuring and managing our AWS RDS instance for database.
- Installing, configuring, and maintaining MySQL databases with more than 50 tables.
- Optimizing SQL queries to improve fetch time across tables
- Setting up, configuring and maintaining our content delivery AWS EC2 instance.
- Building Music Content delivery server and manager (NICK 2.0) with PHP.
- Building NICK 2.0 APIs.
- Maintaining the content delivery server algorithm which parsed the XML from DDEX metadata into the database and moved the MP3 to S3 for permanent storage.
- Devops of the content delivery AWS EC2 instance.
- Mastering and working extensively with SSH.

- Configuring and maintaining our AWS S3 storage server which housed hundreds of thousands of MP3 data.
- Integrating AWS S3 SDK into the Android app for user content management.
- Working extensively with Android Studio, PHPStorm, WinSCP, PuTTY, FileZilla, Git Bash, TeamViewer, Trello, Skype, Slack, etc.

Android Development Lecturer, 08/2016 to 11/2016

Springlight Technology Ltd, Uyo, Nigeria

- Prepared lecture materials for Android app development.
- Trained staff and students on the fundamentals of Android app development.

National Youth Service Corps, Mathematics Teacher, 04/2017 to 03/2018

Federal Government Girls College, Ganjuwa L.G.A, Bauchi State, Nigeria

- Taught and tested the students in Junior Secondary Mathematics.
- Assisted the Mathematics Head of Department to set questions for Mathematics terminal examination.

Education

Bachelor of Mechanical Engineering (B.ENG MECH.), 09/2010 to 09/2015 **University Of Benin** - Benin city, Nigeria

Projects

- I developed Datura Firewall app with my team at CalyxOS https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/platform packages apps Firewall
- I developed Buttercup Feedback app with my team at CalyxOS https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/platform_packages_apps_Buttercup
- I developed Bubbles Guide app with my team at CalyxOS https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/platform_packages_apps_Bubbles
- Designed and built SoftPowerButton https://github.com/esecoder/softpowerbutton
- Contributed code to Tella Android app <u>https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.hzontal.tella</u> <u>https://github.com/Horizontal-org/Tella-Android</u>
- Contributed code to Zammad Android client. An API library for Zammad Helpdesk https://github.com/KirkBushman/zammad-android
- Contributed code to Riseup and Bitmask VPN Android app
 https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=se.leap.riseupvpn
 https://oxacab.org/leap/bitmask-vpn
 <a href="https://oxacab.org/
- I developed the Calyx Blossom Muzei source system app with my team at CalyxOS https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/blossom
- I developed the Calyx Muzei wallpaper app with my team at CalyxOS https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/muzei
- I developed and deployed to the cloud the MePlaylist Music Streaming App https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=app.meplaylist.com.meplay

- I handled technical analysis, design, development of various mobiles apps for clients working with our consultancy
- I designed and developed the NAPTIP App, a crime reporting app portal for the National Agency for the Prohibition of Trafficking in Persons, Abuja Nigeria. https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=ng.gov.naptip.app.android
- I designed the database and contributed to the APIs for MePlaylist Music Streaming web app http://app.meplaylist.com
- I developed some APIs for TuneAfrique music distribution platform https://tuneafrique.com
- I have some App UI/UX design samples to help assess my design skills. https://drive.google.com/open?id=1c9JXIUvMsLQAyalArUnvUI2hiQnxFd1A
- I designed and developed CryptoTracker: open source project for tracking cryptocurrencies BTC and ETH in 20 currencies around the world. https://github.com/EseCoder/cryptotracker
- I designed and developed Zysit Android app and Website for Event seats reservation and management (Awaiting launch) https://zysit.com
- I conceptualized, designed and developed a Mobile Payment Android App with proprietary offline capabilities. (Awaiting launch)
- During my time at the University of Benin I designed and developed CBT Software
 Solution for the defunct Fantrix Integrated Solutions
- During my training at NIIT, Benin city, I designed and developed a Bluetooth Chatting and Video Calling Java Software for certification defense.

Training

Oracle Certificate in Core Java and Web Component Development in Java (OCJP) 2013, NIIT - Benin city, Nigeria

I learned the Java programming language and Web components design and development.
 This course also taught me advanced skills in JDBC, JSP, Java EE as well as various other Java component libraries.

Android Development - Andela Android Development Training in partnership with Udacity and Google through the Andela Learning Community programme (2018)

 I was awarded a scholarship on the Android Development track which further advanced my knowledge in building mobile applications

Android Development - Google Developer Website (2015)

• I used the Google Developer website to up-skill my knowledge on Android Development with a focus on API documentation.

Kotlin Development - Codecademy (2021)

https://codecademy.com

• I used codecademy, a massive open online course (MOOC), to practise and learn with Kotlin.

Web Development - Codecademy (2015)

https://codecademy.com

• I used codecademy, a massive open online course (MOOC), to learn practical skill with several languages, including HTML, CSS, JavaScript and PHP.

Social Media

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/eseudom

Reference

Available on request